ABDO E. ABDO

501 Forest Avenue, Palo Alto, CA 94301 Cell Phone: 212-810-1054 Personal email: aabdo2006@kellogg.northwestern.edu

EXECUTIVE SUMMARY

Performance-driven executive with extensive M&A and strategic investment experience in the technology and cleantech industry. Self starter, comfortable operating in small as well as large team settings; effective communicator at all levels of the organization. Key skills include strong financial modeling, solid understanding of M&A investment and accounting practices, strategic planning, and leading the M&A and divestiture processes from start to finish. Strong ability to develop and lead teams to execute complex projects. Author of 12 US patents.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Applied Materials, Corporate Business Development, Santa Clara, CA

June 2009 – November 2011

Manager, Mergers and Acquisitions

Reporting to head of M&A and strategic investments, responsible for all aspects of deal sourcing and execution across Applied Materials business units; engaging with senior management to identify high value prospects, developing and evaluating business cases, negotiating & executing deals. Responsibilities also include overseeing due diligence, estimating P&L impact and establishing value drivers and performance metrics for completed transactions.

Selected completed transactions:

- Advent Solar, Inc., privately-held company that designs and manufactures high efficiency silicon-based photovoltaic solar cells and modules. Responsibilities included working with business unit teams to build investment case, preparing investment recommendation to CEO and board of directors. Led due diligence team comprised of functional leads and outside advisors, worked with legal counsel on term sheet and key transaction agreement elements.
- Semitool, Inc., publicly-held semi-conductor capital equipment company, transaction value is \$364M. Responsibilities included directing analysts in building initial valuation models, led effort with business unit in building investment case, and obtaining the necessary approvals by senior executives and board of directors. Led full due diligence team in validating investment case and preparing the necessary presentations for final approval by board of directors.
- Varian Semiconductor, Inc. publicly-held semi-conductor and solar equipment company, transaction value is \$4.9B. Responsibilities included leading multifunctional due diligence team to validate the investment thesis and valuation model. Reported findings to investment committee and board of directors.
- Led an auction process to sell an \$80m business unit, this included preparing sale materials, contacting buyers, performing management presentations, negotiating term sheets, definitive and transition services agreements.
- Led negotiations to acquire a software startup in yield prediction and performance analytics.
- Collaborated with outside consulting firm to create post-acquisition performance tracking, worked with business unit leaders to identify and set financial targets and report quarterly results to board of directors.
- Advised business unit heads on several M&A opportunities, including industry review, strategic fit and buy vs. build analysis.
- Led quarterly reviews of acquisition pipeline with CEO and investment committee. Collaborated with divisions to identify targets that address portfolio gaps and performed initial screening of potential M&A targets.

• Worked with internal teams to establish robust divestiture processes and practice. Developed process and framework materials that are being across divestiture projects.

IBM, Corporate Development, Armonk, NY

June 2006 – June 2009

Associate, Mergers and Acquisitions

Performed the process of sourcing, evaluating, and executing acquisition opportunities. This included financial valuations, assembling and leading due diligence teams and external advisors, assisting with deal terms and agreements, developing post-acquisition integration plans.

• Co-led the signing and closing of five acquisitions, collectively contributing over \$600M of incremental revenue in the first year and exceeding IBM investment criteria. Led a team of 60+ IBM subject matter experts and external advisors on numerous due diligence engagements.

Select completed transactions:

- Cognos Inc., a publicly-held software company with a transaction value of \$5B, largest software company in Canada. Executed all aspects of the deal, from early stage development of investment case and valuation, due diligence, assisting with legal agreements, including term sheet, negotiating covenants, reps and warranties, and retention agreements of key executives. Managed post-signing regulatory filings, working with IBM legal counsel and external advisors.
- DataMirror Corp., a publicly-held software company with a transaction value of \$170M.
- ILog SA., a publicly-held provider of rules management systems, headquartered in Gentilly, France, with transaction value of \$340M.
- Led several high profile strategy projects initiated by IBM CEO and Board of Directors including:
 - Exploring strategic alternatives for under performing assets. Deals collectively valued at over \$18B
 - Performing competitive threat assessment of M&A strategy within market.
- Collaborated with IBM business units, investment banks, venture capital and private equity community to source investment opportunities and develop deal pipeline that meet IBM's strategic and financial objectives.
- Developed strong skills in financial modeling, valuation, and accounting practices. Developed training programs for MBA interns and junior analysts on financial models.

IBM, Software Group, Rochester, MN

January 1999- June 2006

Software Product Development Manager

- Managed cross-functional team in delivering the first generation virtualization product to compete with VMware. Offering. Product won IBM's 2005 Innovation Excellence Award.
- Successfully performed people management responsibilities for 21+ employees, including conducting annual performance reviews, coaching and career development, managing performance issues, and recruiting and retaining top talent.
- Co-developed product strategy and go-to-market plans, and presented to IBM top 50 customers.

Lead Architect

• Co-led IBM DB2 Re-engineering, 2-year project with development budget of \$60M, designed and developed DB2 Statistics Engine. Effort contributed 12 Patents to IBM Intellectual Property portfolio.

- Served as a client advocate executive for two major accounts, Cabela's and SPSS, assisted on closing sales opportunities in the range of \$5M.
- Received IBM's Outstanding Technical Achievement Award and selected in IBM technical resource program.

EDUCATION

KELLOGG SCHOOL OF MANAGEMENT, NORTHWESTERN UNIVERSITY

Masters of Business Administration, concentration in Finance and Strategy

Evanston, IL June 2006

SCHOOL OF ENGINEERING, ALEXANDRIA UNIVERSITY

Bachelor of Science in Computer Science and Automatic Control

Alexandria, Egypt August 1998

ADDITIONAL INFORMATION

Fluent in Arabic. US Citizen.

Granted IBM Invention Achievement Award 3 times, reached 3rd Invention Plateau in less than 5 years. Avid soccer player, cyclist, and windsurfer. Also enjoy traveling and reading.